<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<actions>
  <h1>Introduction</h1>

  <p>
    This document aims to comprehensively document all of the OpenFlow actions
    and instructions, both standard and non-standard, supported by Open
    vSwitch, regardless of origin.  The document includes information of
    interest to Open vSwitch users, such as the semantics of each supported
    action and the syntax used by Open vSwitch tools, and to developers seeking
    to build controllers and switches compatible with Open vSwitch, such as the
    wire format for each supported message.
  </p>

  <h2>Actions</h2>

  <p>
    In this document, we define an <dfn>action</dfn> as an OpenFlow action,
    which is a kind of command that specifies what to do with a packet.
    Actions are used in OpenFlow flows to describe what to do when the flow
    matches a packet, and in a few other places in OpenFlow.  Each version of
    the OpenFlow specification defines standard actions, and beyond that many
    OpenFlow switches, including Open vSwitch, implement extensions to the
    standard.
  </p>

  <p>
    OpenFlow groups actions in two ways: as an <dfn>action list</dfn> or an
    <dfn>action set</dfn>, described below.
  </p>

  <h3>Action Lists</h3>

  <p>
    An <dfn>action list</dfn>, a concept present in every version of OpenFlow,
    is simply an ordered sequence of actions.  The OpenFlow specifications
    require a switch to execute actions within an action list in the order
    specified, and to refuse to execute an action list entirely if it cannot
    implement the actions in that order [OpenFlow 1.0, section 3.3], with one
    exception: when an action list outputs multiple packets, the switch may
    output the packets in an order different from that specified.  Usually,
    this exception is not important, especially in the common case when the
    packets are output to different ports.
  </p>

  <h3>Action Sets</h3>

  <p>
    OpenFlow 1.1 introduced the concept of an <dfn>action set</dfn>.  An action
    set is also a sequence of actions, but the switch reorders the actions and
    drops duplicates according to rules specified in the OpenFlow
    specifications.  Because of these semantics, some actions cannot be
    included in an action set.
  </p>

  <p>
    Open vSwitch
  </p>

  <h2>Instructions</h2>

  <p>
    Every version of OpenFlow includes actions.  OpenFlow 1.1 introduced the
    higher-level, related concept of <dfn>instructions</dfn>.  In OpenFlow 1.1
    and later, actions within a flow are always encapsulated within an
    instruction.  This document describes both actions and instructions.
  </p>

  <group title="Output">
    <p>
      These actions send a packet to a physical port or a controller.  A packet
      that never encounters an output action on its trip through the Open
      vSwitch pipeline is effectively dropped.  Because actions are executed in
      order, a packet modification action that is not eventually followed by an
      output action will not have an externally visible effect.
    </p>

    <action name="OUTPUT">
      <syntax><var>port</var></syntax>
      <syntax>output:<var>port</var></syntax>
      <p>
        Outputs the packet to OpenFlow port <var>port</var>.  If
        <var>port</var> is the packet's input port, the packet is not output.
        The <var>port</var> may be a numeric port number in the range 0 to
        65,535, although Open vSwitch only assigns port numbers in the range 1
        through 62,279 to ports.
      </p>


    </action>
  </group>

</actions>
